<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Decision Making on Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck</title>
    <link>/categories/decision-making/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Decision Making on Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>{year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 14:23:40 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/decision-making/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Professor priming &amp;#8211; or not</title>
      <link>/post/2017-11-13-professor-priming-or-not/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 14:23:40 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-11-13-professor-priming-or-not/</guid>
      <description>This was my first contribution to a Registered Replication Report (RRR). Being one of 40 participating labs was an interesting exercise &amp;#8211; it might seem straightforward to run the same study in different labs, but we learned that such small things as ü, ä and ö can generate a huge amount of problems and work (read this if you are into these kind of things).  Here is one of the central results:   So overall not a lot of action &amp;#8230; our lab was actually the one with larges effect size (in the predicted direction).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A short history of process tracing</title>
      <link>/post/2017-10-31-a-short-history-of-process-tracing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 00:10:34 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-10-31-a-short-history-of-process-tracing/</guid>
      <description>Finally out (already mentioned earlier this year) &amp;#8211; now in it&amp;#8217;s full glory @ Current Directions in Psychological Science.
Good Stuff.
a little process tracing history together with the delightful @dggoldst https://t.co/svGBLYcAZv#processtracing #JDM  &amp;mdash; Michael Schulte (@SchulteMi) October 31, 2017  &amp;nbsp;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Growing up to be old</title>
      <link>/post/2017-04-12-growing-up-to-be-old/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 07:45:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-04-12-growing-up-to-be-old/</guid>
      <description>Some papers have somewhat weird starting points &amp;#8211; this one had an awesome starting point &amp;#8211; Lake Louise (Canada):
In a little suite we (Joe Johnson, Ulf Böckenholt, Dan Goldstein, Jay Russo, Nikki Sullivan, Martijn Willemsen) sat down during a conference called the &amp;#8216;Choice Symposium&amp;#8216; and started working on an overview paper about the history and current status of different process tracing methods. One central result (why can&amp;#8217;t all papers be like that) is the figure below where we try to locate many process tracing methods on the two dimensions: temporal resolution and distortion risk (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Something about reverse inference</title>
      <link>/post/2017-04-12-something-about-reverse-inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 07:29:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-04-12-something-about-reverse-inference/</guid>
      <description>Often, when we run process tracing studies (e.g., eye-tracking, mouse-tracking, thinking-aloud) we talk about cognitive processes (things we can&amp;#8217;t observe) in a way that they are actually and directly observable. This is pretty weird &amp;#8211; which becomes obvious when looking at the data from the paper below. In this paper we simply instruct participants to follow a strategy when making choices between risky gamble problems. Taking the example of fixation duration we see that there is surprisingly litte difference between calculating an expected value, using a heuristic (priority heuristic) and just making decisions without instructions (no instruction) &amp;#8230; maybe we should rethink our mapping of observation to cognitive processes a bit?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strava</title>
      <link>/post/2016-08-30-strava/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 00:25:21 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016-08-30-strava/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Paper on pychodiagnosis and eye-tracking</title>
      <link>/post/2015-11-10-new-paper-on-pychodiagnosis-and-eye-tracking/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 03:39:33 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-11-10-new-paper-on-pychodiagnosis-and-eye-tracking/</guid>
      <description>Cilia Witteman and Nanon Spaanjaars (my dutch connection) worked together on a piece on whether psychodiagnosticians improve over time (they don&amp;#8217;t) in their ability to classify symptoms to DSM categories. This turned out to be a pretty cool paper combining eye-tracking data with a practical, and hopefully, relevant question.
Schulte-Mecklenbeck, M., Spaanjaars, N.L., &amp;amp; Witteman, C.L.M. (in press). The (in)visibility of psychodiagnosticians&amp;#8217; expertise. Journal of Behavioral Decision Making. http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/bdm.1925
 Abstract  This study investigates decision making in mental health care.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>the way I am seen, by people who know (and like) me</title>
      <link>/post/2015-07-13-the-way-i-am-seen-by-people-who-know-and-like-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2015 01:17:07 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-07-13-the-way-i-am-seen-by-people-who-know-and-like-me/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>about illusions</title>
      <link>/post/2015-03-11-about-illusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:58:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-03-11-about-illusions/</guid>
      <description>Andrew Gelman talked about a really old paper I did together with Anton Kühberger ages ago. It was actually the first paper / &amp;#8216;real&amp;#8217; scientific project I was involved in.
It generated quite the buzz over its 20 year lifespan and was cited a whopping 13 times (stats look good without y-axis) &amp;#8230;

&amp;nbsp;
&amp;nbsp;
&amp;nbsp;
Going back to it, I was happy to see that we already talked about replication (and were very reluctant to push the button harder &amp;#8211; as we would have not been able to get through the reviews, I guess) &amp;#8230; Things have changed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving an idea into business</title>
      <link>/post/2015-02-07-moving-an-idea-into-business/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2015 15:15:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-02-07-moving-an-idea-into-business/</guid>
      <description>Recently Ryan Murphy and myself realised that a startup here in Berlin features ideas of our 2011 Flashlight paper.
Well, the guys at attensee.com did a great job taking the idea we had much further we ever thought one would be able to take it &amp;#8230;
Here is a feature I totally love &amp;#8211; a live heat map of what you are looking at &amp;#8230; awesome!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Die Zeit Wissen &amp;#8230; schreibt über Essensentscheidungen</title>
      <link>/post/2014-08-22-die-zeit-wissen-schreibt-uber-essensentscheidungen/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2014 14:26:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-08-22-die-zeit-wissen-schreibt-uber-essensentscheidungen/</guid>
      <description>Mal was Längeres zu unseren Lieblingsthemen: Essen und Entscheidungsforschung &amp;#8230; Enjoy!
2014-08-19_DieZeitWissen-wie-sie-beim-essen-die-richtigen-entscheidungen-treffen</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When something old &amp;#8230;</title>
      <link>/post/2014-05-07-when-something-old/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2014 01:12:06 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-05-07-when-something-old/</guid>
      <description>Schulte-Mecklenbeck, M., &amp; Kühberger, A. (2014). Out of sight – out of mind? Information acquisition patterns in risky choice framing. Polish Psychological Bulletin, 45, 21–28. I teamed up with Anton Kühberger to write about one of our old, favorite topics: framing and process tracing &amp;#8230; Here is the abstract:
We investigate whether risky choice framing, i.e., the preference of a sure over an equivalent risky option when choosing among gains, and the reverse when choosing among losses, depends on redundancy and density of information available in a task.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New paper on food choice and simple heuristics</title>
      <link>/post/2013-08-16-new-paper-on-food-choice-and-simple-heuristics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2013 06:57:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2013-08-16-new-paper-on-food-choice-and-simple-heuristics/</guid>
      <description>We got a new paper out on how people (consumers) use simple rules to make food choices. This is work in collaboration with the Nestlé Research Center in Lausanne.
Here is the reference:
Schulte-Mecklenbeck, M., Sohn, M., Bellis, E., Martin, N., &amp; Hertwig, R. (2013). A Lack of Appetite for Information and Computation: Simple Heuristics in Food Choice. Appetite, 71, 242–251. Abstract
The predominant, but largely untested, assumption in research on food choice is that people obey the classic commandments of rational behavior: they carefully look up every piece of relevant information, weight each piece according to subjective importance, and then combine them into a judgment or choice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On writing in social science</title>
      <link>/post/2012-02-03-on-writing-in-social-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2012 02:37:44 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2012-02-03-on-writing-in-social-science/</guid>
      <description>Malcom Gladwell (author of Blink and Tipping point) meets Dan Ariely (author of Predictively Irrational and Ig Nobel Prize Winner) to chat on what are good strategies in selecting topics to write about and the difficulties of wading through complex information &amp;#8230; Its called a research chat</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>how decisions deplete and breaks help</title>
      <link>/post/2011-08-18-how-decisions-deplete-and-breaks-help/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2011 22:31:18 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2011-08-18-how-decisions-deplete-and-breaks-help/</guid>
      <description>The New York Times published a nice overview of the work on decision making and ego depletion (often ego depletion is used as a synonym with resource depletion, which is somewhat confusing because of the use of the later in economy to described the situation when raw materials are exhausted in a region).
A new paper from Jonathan Levav (now at Standford &amp;#8211; congrats!) is prominently featured in the above article.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog-attack</title>
      <link>/post/2011-03-01-blog-attack/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 01:58:43 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2011-03-01-blog-attack/</guid>
      <description>Here is what Andrew Gelman writes about an interview Colin Camerer gave on Spousomonics &amp;#8230; Looking forward to Camerer&amp;#8217;s reply &amp;#8230;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How WEIRD subjects can be overcome &amp;#8230; a comment on Henrich et al.</title>
      <link>/post/2009-12-12-how-weird-subjects-can-be-overcome-a-comment-on-henrich-et-al/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2009 06:11:14 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2009-12-12-how-weird-subjects-can-be-overcome-a-comment-on-henrich-et-al/</guid>
      <description>Joe Henrich published a target article in BBS talking about how economics and psychology base their research on WEIRD (Western, Educated, Industrialized, Rich and Democratic) subjects.
Here is the whole abstract:
&amp;#8212;
Behavioral scientists routinely publish broad claims about human psychology and behavior in the world’s top journals based on samples drawn entirely from Western, Educated, Industrialized, Rich and Democratic (WEIRD) societies. Researchers—often implicitly—assume that either there is little variation across human populations, or that these “standard subjects” are as representative of the species as any other population.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Priority Heuristic comment</title>
      <link>/post/2008-03-17-priority-heuristic-comment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2008 12:55:58 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2008-03-17-priority-heuristic-comment/</guid>
      <description>We (Johnson, Schulte-Mecklenbeck, &amp;amp; Willemsen, 2008) have got a new paper out that comments on the Priority Heuristic as described in Brandstaetter, Gigerenzer and Hertwig, 2006.
Resolution of debates in cognition usually comes from the introduction of constraints in the form of new data about either the process or representation. Decision research, in contrast, has relied predominantly on testing models by examining their fit to choices. The authors examine a recently proposed choice strategy, the priority heuristic, which provides a novel account of how people make risky choices.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>