<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Replication on Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck</title>
    <link>/categories/replication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Replication on Michael Schulte-Mecklenbeck</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>{year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 21:16:40 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/replication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A letter to the black goat</title>
      <link>/post/2018-07-30-a-letter-to-the-black-goat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 21:16:40 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-07-30-a-letter-to-the-black-goat/</guid>
      <description>I wrote this letter to the black goat podcast &amp;#8230; will update here if I hear back from them &amp;#8230;
&amp;nbsp;
Dear goaters (is this a good way to address the three of you?),
   I attended SIPS some weeks ago (first timer). I was unsure what to expect but got a lot of bang for my buck (which is great) &amp;#8211; as a side note I would recommend first timers to try to go there with a concrete project or question or problem, I think there is a good chance to find people with similar issues interested in collaborations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professor priming &amp;#8211; or not</title>
      <link>/post/2017-11-13-professor-priming-or-not/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 14:23:40 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-11-13-professor-priming-or-not/</guid>
      <description>This was my first contribution to a Registered Replication Report (RRR). Being one of 40 participating labs was an interesting exercise &amp;#8211; it might seem straightforward to run the same study in different labs, but we learned that such small things as ü, ä and ö can generate a huge amount of problems and work (read this if you are into these kind of things).  Here is one of the central results:   So overall not a lot of action &amp;#8230; our lab was actually the one with larges effect size (in the predicted direction).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The root of the problem</title>
      <link>/post/2017-11-13-the-root-of-the-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 05:44:06 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-11-13-the-root-of-the-problem/</guid>
      <description>One of the root causes of where we are (as a science) in psychology and many other disciplines in terms of reproducibility of key (and other) results could not be better summed up than by the man himself Daryl Bem (2002):
“If a datum suggests a new hypothesis, try to find additional evidence for it elsewhere in the data. If you see dim traces of interesting patterns, try to reorganize the data to bring them into bolder relief.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Everything you believe in is wrong &amp;#8211; or is it simply terrorism?</title>
      <link>/post/2016-09-20-everything-you-believe-in-is-wrong-or-is-it-simply-terrorism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 00:15:15 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016-09-20-everything-you-believe-in-is-wrong-or-is-it-simply-terrorism/</guid>
      <description>The replication crisis has many interesting effects on how people (and scientists) think about Psychology (and, of course, other fields) &amp;#8230; Here is a nice summary of effects that are hard to replicate. Among them &amp;#8216;classics&amp;#8217; like the power pose or the big brother eyes.
A lot is happening because of these new insights in terms of research (e.g., replication studies) and communication (e.g., Fritz Strack on Facebook).
And then this: Susan Fiske in an upcoming piece in the APS Observer &amp;#8230; I am really struggling with this rhetoric &amp;#8211; Daniel Lakens to the rescue 🙂</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Everything is fucked &amp;#8230;</title>
      <link>/post/2016-08-12-everything-is-fucked/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2016 00:05:23 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016-08-12-everything-is-fucked/</guid>
      <description>This syllabus of an (obviously) awesome class has a ton of good reads:
Everything is fucked: The&amp;nbsp;syllabus
by Sanjay Srivastava
I would have two additions:
 A multi lab replication project on ego-depletion (Hagger &amp;amp; Chatzisarantis, 2016) And the response from Roy Baumeister and Kathleen D. Vohs  It&amp;#8217;s a really good statement of how f&amp;#8230; up things are (in addition to all the other good examples above) &amp;#8230;
“A new scientific truth does not triumph by convincing its opponents and making them see the light, but rather because its opponents eventually die, and a new generation grows up that is familiar with it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>